Can a vegetable have inheritance from a fish?
Can you become a copy of your grandmother and can a bacterium make medicine?
The answer is yes.
Strange but true.
And everything has to do with genetic engineering.
In 1865, the Austrian monk presents Gregor Mendel-
-How properties appear to be inherited from one generation to another.
This after he studied 29,000 pea plant-
That the DNA molecule and all its genes gave an organism its properties.
Since then, a huge effort has been made to map the organisms' DNA-
-to try to understand which gene is linked to which trait.
Hand in hand with this a new technology has grown - genetic engineering.
It has made it possible to change genes of living organisms.
For a long time we have characterized animals through breeding and plants through processing.
But it has taken many generations before you have been able to see a result.
After realizing the importance
-There more experiments began.
One such example is the sheep dolly-
-A of the first genetic engineering experiments carried out on a mammal.
The very purpose was to investigate-
-If it was possible to clone, make an exact copy, of a mammal.
One moved a cell nucleus into a fertilized egg from another sheep-
-To give the other characteristics.
You use bacteria to help.
The desired gene is moved into a DNA molecule that is inserted into the bacterium.
You then enter the bacterium into a cell on the organism you want to change.
The new molecule can marry in the DNA.
It changes the genetic mass.
One can take a gene from an ice ocean fish and place it in a vegetable-
-and make it more cold-resistant-
-or make a crop that is more durable to pesticides-
-So that the weeds die but not the crop.
The views on this fall apart.
The skepticals believe that there are risks in manipulating the genetic mass.
In Sweden, foods that contain more than 1 % GMO must be labeled.
The method would not work on a human being.
Therefore, it became a fuss when an extraordinary discovery was made in 2012.
A method that could be used on human-
-Top the technology to a whole new level.
Instead of adding genes, it is about changing the inheritance mass.
I'm talking about Crispr-Cas9 or the "Gen Sax" which received the Nobel Prize in 2020.
It was Emmanuelle Charpentier and Jennifer Doudna who came up with the method.